says, "Bante, since childhood, I've been
trapped in self-hatred, seeing only
ugliness, failure, and burden in my
reflection. People say that I'm too
harsh on myself. I know it's true. Yet
the cycle persists. I shun mirrors, even
fear new beginnings, and hide myself,
convinced I will never be good enough.
How does one escape such a prison of
selfhatred?
Well, I mean, whether it's the
self-hatred or self-indulgence,
um, it stems from the mind that's that's
untamed and has had
it its own way for too long. So whatever
So whatever
intense moods or emotions you're going
through, the intensity of those things
comes from the wildness of the mind. You
know, like everybody has times or
periods or
um moods of self-hatred or or um as I
said, self aggrandizing whatever is the
opposite of it. Um, but then they
usually, you know, would not
necessarily dwell on those things as
long as some other people might for
whatever circumstantial
reasons. So, you need to recognize that
the problem is not
really whether you have thoughts of
self-hatred or thoughts that you're the
greatest person in the world. The
problem is that the intensity of those
thoughts reveals the the degree of
the of your mind. How much it's not
actually tamed, how much it it disregard
you. That's the real problem. So
self-loathing, self-hatred is not uh
something that you've well it's it's a
it's a symptom. It's a symptom. Yeah. If
you're reaching the point of like
chronic what that person seems to
describe like chronic self-loathing.
Yeah. It means like chronic
untamedness of its mind that just keeps
picking that for whatever reason that
it's irrelevant actually. Why? Why is it
like this not not in some other way?
Because if it weren't that way, it would
have been some other way. Because that
lack of teness, that wilderness of that
mind will find its ways of expressing
itself. the the degree of how wild it
is, how how um how little regard it has
for you. So the the training of
purification is the training of that
animal and that in itself would then
reduce the intensity of whatever that
animals animal chooses to uh engage with
whatever the habits are whether it's
self-loading or this or that.
Um it comes from the same place
that the mind desires things. Yeah. The
mind desires things and if that desire
has been kept has been allowed to
persist and proliferate unchecked, it
will become pathological in a way. The
desire it will reach the extremes that
it's now just just unbearable. But the
only reason is that is such is because
the mind has been allowed to to to sort
of walk those pathways repeatedly over
and over and over again and further and
further and further and now it's just
like a smooth canal. It just flies thing
just mind just just slides through it
straight at the at the end point where
it left off. So that needs to be undone.
that needs to be prevented from from
proliferating, from getting worse, needs
to be tamed. And the mind will it's
going to resist
it. It's going to resist it. That's why
even if people did not have
self-loathing to begin with, when they
start keeping the precepts and trying to
tame the animal and maybe, you know, put
a lid on their desires, they're going to
start self-loading. The mind will then
turn against itself, against you. Yeah.
It's literally like the wild dog.
If you were to have a wild dog next to
you and constantly you're throwing raw
meat to it, it's it's fine. It's fine.
It's just because it sees all what it
wants. You're giving it the moment you
stop it starts to growl at you or
whoever and gets agitated. Let alone if
you now keep it hungry for a while.
Yeah. But that is the
training. So that's the entire gradual
training. They're laying down the
foundations of of virtue, precepts,
sense restraint to basically contain
that animal when it starts to self-loa
for right reasons for the reasons of um
depriving it of those of those depraved
ways, desires and so
on. But yeah, it's difficult
uh not to so you self-loathing and then
you I shouldn't be doing this. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's the same like
same as we spoke about like uh with
anxiety like oh I shouldn't be feeling
this. It's like no it's not a problem.
It's a symptom. So so self-loathing.
Yeah. You shouldn't you shouldn't be
like you shouldn't allow
yourself the images associated with it
to to like wallow in it and make it
worse. But you need to recognize you
also need to um teach yourself to stop
regarding that as a problem and start
seeing it as a symptom.
So it's a symptom of the untamed mind
that when I'm not self-loathing I am
enabling in its untamed
ways because yeah
sure you can be you can leave your your
mind untamed you can allow its desires
you think it's not a problem
self-loading can come up and then I can
tell you well just calm down uh embrace
it be you know accept don't resist it
calm down in the body. Feel the
sensations. Watch your nostrils.
Concentrate. Forget about it. And it
it's Yeah, it feels like, oh, it went
away. Wow, it helped me. But ask
yourself, if I tell you to do that and
you do that, what are the chances of it
coming back?
100%. You already know the answer. It's
100% it's going to come back. So then do
it again what I told you. And you think
now the chances have been reduced? No.
You might like to think they'll be
reduced, but you can do it 10 years.
Whenever it comes, you do this, it's
going to keep coming back. And you
already know that even from the start.
So believing that it will somehow
magically resolve itself through your
calming techniques and learning how to
be calm amidst these these things. It's
like you already know that it's that it
doesn't work that way. You already know
that it's just like wishful thinking.
So if it gets too much whatever
come yourself whichever way you've been
calming yourself but that's completely
has nothing to do with uprooting it or
practicing rightly.
The only reason you need to calm
yourself up is because you still calm
yourself down is because you still take
up the symptom as a problem. It's
because you're still not seeing where
the real problem is. So you're just
pasting. Just comes
up. Put it down. Comes up. Put it down.
Comes down. Put it down. But why is it
coming up? Well, it's coming up because
the mind does not respect you, does not
listen to you. And uh it leads you. You
are not leading
it. And there is no magical recipe for
that. They will just help you through
through mere coping when things get too
much and then just magically they
resolve themselves and you know you go
into like a self hypnosis. Sorry, I mean
meditation um every now and then feel
pleasant watch sensations and then that
just just miraculously Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
is just making this mind less wild less
sort of u disrespectful that towards me
less self-loathing. It's like no. And
even if you make a determination to
constantly stay on the level of of of
calming whatever comes
up again you are still managing the
symptoms. The only reason you have such
thoughts and by the way the same even if
it's I said even if it's not the extreme
um extremely proliferated cases of
self-loathing or conceit or the nature
of the five hindrances is already that
the nature of the of sensuality is
already that the nature of ill will it's
already the same. That's like the
thoughts that come up with it. You need
to recognize the symptom of a problem of
an untamed mind. If the mind were tamed,
these things wouldn't come up in the
first place. I would already be calm
amidst the disturbances. Yeah. So, I got
to tame my mind, not exactly. So, do you
really want and see but that's the irony
of it. Even people that practice the
calming as coping think it's Yeah. Will
they do it because they underneath it?
As I said, they believe that it will
lead to a substantial calming of the
more fundamental kind. But as I said,
just ask yourself how many times you've
been doing it. And if you were
honest, is there any
degree like you might say, "Oh, things
don't come up as much as before." But
that's because maybe you changed your
environment. Maybe your coping became
more um your management coping became
more uh quicker because you've been
doing it for so long. But fundamentally
just if you boil it all down and ask
yourself, yeah, but can it still arise
in the first place? Is there is there
nothing that I could sort of put in
between so that these thoughts, these
states of mind can't even come up? And
the answer is no. You don't even know
where to apply that. You wouldn't even
know where to begin because you've been
practicing at the wrong place. So in the
wrong place. The place the thing to put
in between. What is the thing that you
can put in between that so that it
doesn't come up again? Yeah. Well, you
already know that your decisions, your
decisions, your non- action towards the
unbeneficial things. Your sense
restraint, your virtue is already what
you're putting in between. Now, it's not
going to remove the persisting besetting
unpleasant symptoms like you're treating the
symptoms like you're treating the
infection with the
antibiotics. The wound still hurts,
still itches, but it's being treated
from in the from the inside.
Mhm. And if you stick to the regime and
follow the right diet and not aggravate
it to scratching or putting random crap
on top of it that's actually making it
worse, you will heal up and then you
will not have a need to to learn how to
scratch skillfully and manage and do
this or that. So this is the same. You
are addressing the
mind. Now somebody might ask well can I
do both?
Can it be addressing the mind and coping
and doing meditation techniques and
calming? Then you have to ask yourself,
well, exactly. Yeah. Um, if I'm
addressing the mind rightly, that should
already be calming. So, if I need to
address the mind and continue my calming
techniques, I'm not addressing the mind.
So, it's addressing things in the roots.
If you're pulling the roots, you don't
need to be constantly trimming the ever
growing branches.
So if you think you you can or you
should be doing both, it's because
you're not actually pulling out the
roots. So when things get too much, as I
said, you're already going to be giving
into the management even without making
a conscious misguided practice out of
it. You are already coping
By not giving in, you are already
coping. By practicing restraint, you're
already coping. Yeah. But you're kind of
coping in a less wrong way. That's very
restraint in itself. It's not going to
free you from it, but it's certainly not
going to make it worse. It's certainly
going to keep you aligned with where the
roots are, where the mind is, where the
taming is. And that's what I said in the
previous talk. You start doing that
restraint rightly. You don't perpetuate
your wrong views of management and
valuing the release from the symptoms as
the release from the root problem.
Because that's the point. You're going
to fall into that view. If you keep
giving into management of the symptoms
out of the pressure of the problem, it's
because you still believe that abating
of the
symptoms to that extent the problem is
solved. It's like no actually the only
reason you can know the problem is
because of the
symptoms. So you want to use the
recognition and discernment of the
symptoms to keep an eye on the
problem and then if you start practicing
like that even that sense restraint
which is a through means of coping
actually that's like what I said in the
previous talk that
becomes purification. Now that which was
just mere saying no to this, saying no
to that, saying no to things that I
learned are bene
unbeneficial. Well, now that's sort of
coming down to where it should
be, i.e. where the mental training is.
So you're not afraid of thoughts that
come up and try to manage them or or
calm them because it's too unpleasant.
You realize, yeah, that's a symptom.
Doesn't matter. It builds up, comes to
my face trying to make me act. It's all
because of the untamed mind underneath
it. So now by not acting out of this the
So now by not acting out of this the
mind is getting the message that the
pressure he throws at me to act is
working less and less and less and that
calms the
mind again screaming child whenever it
screams you give it what it wants. You
are conveying a message that screaming
works. Look I influence this. I can't
get it myself. I need you to get it for
me. So I scream and threaten and
whatever else and you do it. So it
works. Yeah. Now you encourage that
behavior. And now that it works, each
time it comes up, you practice not
hearing of my screams. You practice
thinking the opposite thoughts. I'll
wait for that and I'll still continue
until you give me what I want. Because
that's usually, well, not usually.
That's always how this ends. When you
finished your calming, you go back to
things that the mind wanted from the
start.
But it's like no, I won't be denying. I
won't be replacing the the thoughts, the
screams of a child. I'll stay with it so
that it sees that I see it and I'm not
giving in to its demands by body, by
speech, by mind. I'm not allowing these
thoughts in a sense of not I'm trying to
get rid of them but in a sense of I'm
not allowing them to take the center
stage take place of of of my activation
of my welcome in accepting them thinking
trying to resolve them basically I won't
be engaged with them yeah but but take
it up take it up solve it solve the
doubt solve the pressure solve the
sensuality solve the hindrance no the
pressure to solve means taking up at a
face value of what the mind's trying to
make me u uh pressured towards
acts. So by not managing it, by staying
with the mind on that level, it sees
that you see it and it sees that you're
not doing what it wants you to do. What
then option? What other option will then
the child have? It's going to tire
itself out and it's going to sit down
quietly and they might even ask you
nicely and it's like yeah and you might have to
and it's like yeah and you might have to
go through that many times because many
times before you would have allowed such
behavior but then after a while then it
realizes that this is better. It
actually realizes, hold on. Actually,
it's it doesn't work. This upset,
kicking, screaming,
threatening just brings me more more
bother, more disturbance. So, I know it
won't let me go in that direction. So, I
might as well not even bother trying.
And then there will be no symptoms for
you to manage.
So, that's the the right taming. The
right taming. Yeah. through right
endurance. through right endurance.
Yeah.
Exactly. Because the whole point of
those thoughts and accepting them at the face
thoughts and accepting them at the face
value as the problem and trying to deal
with them or counter them is the mind is
hidden behind them and you don't see it.
If you're trying to address them, shape
them, manipulate them, change them,
either way you need to take them up. And
by taking them up, you don't see the you
stop seeing the screaming child. All
you're concerned about is what it does
to you. I must stop this. I must count
to that. It's like, no, no, no, no. All
of that, all of that smoke screen
thought is to just make me give in to the fact
is to just make me give in to the fact
that the child is untamed and I'm
enabling it.